<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.8.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-10-24T11:19:08-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title>cbh</title><subtitle>sola dosis facit venenum</subtitle><entry><title>Remember all the things</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/a-workflow-for-remembering-all-that-science-and-also-everything/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remember all the things" /><published>2018-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/a-workflow-for-remembering-all-that-science-and-also-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/a-workflow-for-remembering-all-that-science-and-also-everything/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;we-spend-so-much-time-reading&quot;&gt;We spend so much time reading&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-forgetting&quot;&gt;and forgetting.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like most of you, I read a silly number of books, journal articles, blog posts, whatever. I forget the vast majority of what I read, almost immediately. Chances are, so do you. We’re humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain is a conservative organ, ruthlessly efficient. It kills memories left and right unless it has a really good reason not to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upper limit of short term memory is 6-8 items, on average, and most of what we learn is dumped within a day. However, there is no known upper limit on long-term memory. Let that sink in: &lt;em&gt;no known upper limit&lt;/em&gt;. That is, memory is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;in-finite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: we don’t know how much we can know. We are still exploring the far reaches of long-term memory, and I’m excited. What will be possible after decades of purposeful retention of &lt;em&gt;all the interesting and useful things&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a system cobbled together, with the help of many friends, to convince the brain to have a little mercy.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:10&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:10&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As of October 2018, I’ve been doing this for a few months, and it’s wonderful. It is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desirable_difficulty&quot;&gt;just cumbersome enough&lt;/a&gt; to create conditions for learning, but not so much that I find excuses to skip the process. One difference between this system and what I used to do is the proposed longevity: instead of learning things to pass a class, or do a thing, my goal is to have a coherent way to gain and keep knowledge for life, in all its domains.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:11&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:11&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep this page pretty and focus on process rather than tools, I put specific technologies and commentaries in the clickable footnotes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;find-the-thing&quot;&gt;Find the thing:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;discover &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decide (is it worth my time?) &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hoard&quot;&gt;Hoard:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;so it’s available forevermore (for citation, review, sharing) &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:9&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:9&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;read&quot;&gt;Read:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;annotate (clarify, connect, question) &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;highlight (&lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; what I might want to &lt;em&gt;memorize&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing else.) &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;review&quot;&gt;Review:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;scan annotations and highlights. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decide what to commit to long-term memory. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;retain&quot;&gt;Retain:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;spaced repetition with digital notecards (key points, actionable facts, so what?, lovely quotes, etc.) &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:8&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have suggestions for improvement, questions, tools, or experiences, I would love to hear them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I have a friend who has kept up on his spaced repetition tools from the first US medical licensing exam (10-15k digital flashcards, all the things you learn in the first two years of medical school), and I positively seethe with envy at how little review he will have to do when he takes the second exam. &amp;lt;p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt; Much, if not &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; of my preparation time for the second exam was re-learning things I had learned for the first exam and forgotten. My proof of this was that when I missed practice questions, I could usually search my old flashcard deck and find the exact answer. How much better would life be if I could keep a larger proportion of what I learn, especially if I do it with a system that takes minutes per day? &amp;lt;p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt; Of course, not everything needs to be retained, and the medical licensing exams are, unfortunately, riddled with trivia (i.e. things that are highly testable, but of little use clinically, such as the chromosomal location of a very rare genetic disorder: most doctors will never see the disease, and if they do the last thing that will matter is the location on the chromosome). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:10&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This did not come out of a vacuum. I started with spaced repetition in undergrad under the guidance of a brilliant tutor, then learned from my own students, and am continually indebted to countless classmates and generous souls online. I am deeply grateful to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.harvardmacy.org/index.php&quot;&gt;Harvard Macy Institute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/neilbmehta/&quot;&gt;Dr. Neil Mehta&lt;/a&gt;, in particular, for pushing me to formalize my thinking and get beyond banal “cram and regurgitate” methods for exams and classrooms. They were also the first to give me a framework, and provided many of these tools. These ideas are not new, and have been presented in many forms: my contribution here is a personal system for putting it all together, with my preferred tools. The key addition is spaced repetition, which makes it much more likely for ideas to be imprinted deeply and available quickly. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:10&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:11&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For the philosophic among you: I study artificial intelligence, tools that can consider trillions of variables all at once. The goal is to outsource certain types of thinking that computers are better at, for the benefit of (in my case) people with serious illness. This fits with the basic story of technology: outsource a thing to amplify it (I can pick up a rock: a crane can pick up a house; I can run: an airplane can fly; I can remember some things: Google remembers all the things).
A few technologies, however, are about &lt;em&gt;insourcing&lt;/em&gt;, that is, developing the human element to its maximum. Spaced repetition is one of these technologies, optimized with proven algorithms to maximize how much we can learn and retain. What will be possible when highly developed human memories couple with human creativity, as well as technological support from AI and other advances? So far the research on AI suggests that the very best systems are not solely computers or solely humans, but hybrids, humans working with machines, emphasizing the strengths of both. What happens when we optimize each component? For good and for bad? &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:11&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In order, these are my preferred ways to find things:&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;ol&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;word of mouth&lt;/strong&gt; (in-person, ideally, but a well-crafted newsletter is also a delight. Despite all this technology, I find the best way to address the problem of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/There_are_known_knowns&quot;&gt;unknown unknowns&lt;/a&gt;” is through respected friends and colleagues).&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;purposeful search&lt;/strong&gt; (goal-driven: help this patient, write this paper/blog post, scratch this itch).&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;automatic digests&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://fraserlab.com/2013/09/28/The-Fraser-Lab-method-of-following-the-scientific-literature/&quot;&gt;RSS feeds&lt;/a&gt; of keywords, journals, authors, etc.) I find this approach less useful for students, who have usually not yet differentiated into their specific interests, because any feeds they set up will be too noisy. The link above is great for an overview and examples, but their intake funnel is too wide for my taste. For example, they include the general feed from &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; in addition to highly idiosyncratic feeds. &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; has some interesting stuff and is a blast to browse, but my goal with RSS is to be targeted and &lt;em&gt;save&lt;/em&gt; time: keep the idiosyncracies and ditch &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt;, unless you set up a filter for only the types of articles from &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; you actually care about.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ol&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Quick scan, check out the pictures, skim abstract if available, consider strength of recommendation. Certain people have given me such delicious recommendations in the past that anything they now recommend skips to the head of the reading list. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:9&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diigo.com&quot;&gt;Diigo&lt;/a&gt; for standard web fare, &lt;a href=&quot;https://academicguides.waldenu.edu/library/zotero&quot;&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt; for journal articles with PDFs. We have free, infinitely large Google Drives (for life!) at my university, so I use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1dmdLyZut4rpfPDF8Mt_JhgHLtYkmYS6kggkwn1lSGQQ/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;process described here&lt;/a&gt; to keep the PDFs available in the cloud. If I use this I can read and markup on my phone, computer, whatever, and it will automatically sync. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:9&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For most web-first content, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diigo.com&quot;&gt;Diigo&lt;/a&gt; is great, and I use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.xodo.com/&quot;&gt;Xodo&lt;/a&gt; for PDF markup.
Xodo is the best free full-featured PDF tool I have found: quick, reliable, support for search, annotation (and signatures), highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sumatrapdfreader.org/free-pdf-reader.html&quot;&gt;SumatraPDF&lt;/a&gt; is the fastest PDF reader I have found, great for pure ctrl-F search especially with huge PDF textbooks, but achieves this by being absolutely bare-bones (no handwritten annotation, highlighting, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I also love paper and pen, and because I put the things I want to keep into spaced repetition software, I can usually recycle the paper without fear of losing something important. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Highlighting is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a good method to engage with text and make it sink in. This has been studied, &lt;a href=&quot;https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1021069&quot;&gt;repeatedly&lt;/a&gt;. One of the studies cited in the linked review showed that highlighting &lt;em&gt;impairs&lt;/em&gt; comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;However, if the highlight signals something meaningful and consistent, such as only the kind of information you might want to memorize, you can use the visual cue to quickly find, review, and make decisions about your next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;I still do most of my reading on paper, where highlighting makes review easy. In an app like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.diigo.com&quot;&gt;Diigo&lt;/a&gt; or Kindle, your highlights are extracted into a separate document, which tightens review even further. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Here’s where highlighting only the things you might want to memorize shows its utility.
You may also find that your annotations need annotations, e.g. a question you asked was answered later in the paper. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If something seems worth the &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;5-10 minutes&lt;/a&gt; it will take to make and review a flash card, do it. If not, screw it. Also, develop a low threshold for fixing or deleting cards. This makes card creation in the first place less of a daunting task. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:8&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you keep all your digital notecards in a tool like &lt;a href=&quot;http://ankiguide.com/getting-started-with-anki-srs/&quot;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt;, you will have the spaced repetition part automated, provided you remember to open the app every day.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;If you keep everything in a single Anki deck, regardless of subject, you will also gain the benefit of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/the-interleaving-effect-mixing-it-up-boosts-learning/&quot;&gt;interleaving&lt;/a&gt;. Interleaving is one of a handful of techniques shown to improve memory and understanding, and basically involves mixing material freely without regard for category (e.g. instead of homework with all quadratic equations, mix in all the math from the whole semester in random assortment. In medicine, interleaving is particularly important: if a person comes in with chest pain, heart attack is not the only possibility, and if I had studied only cardiology that month I might fail to consider panic attacks, lung problems, digestive issues, or even blunt trauma, and send the person home after a normal EKG without even looking at their chest or asking any questions. Real life is interleaved.).&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;So I keep my Anki cards all mixed up, such that in a single session I might see bits of useful computer code, friends’ birthdays, dosing regimens for drugs, key points of journal articles, beautiful quotes, etc., in rapid succession. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:8&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="spaced repetition" /><category term="desirable difficulty" /><category term="education" /><category term="learning" /><category term="how-to" /><summary>We spend so much time reading
and forgetting.</summary></entry><entry><title>On the pretentious Latin slogan</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/on-the-slogan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the pretentious Latin slogan" /><published>2018-09-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/on-the-slogan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/on-the-slogan/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;sola-dosis-facit-venenum&quot;&gt;sola dosis facit venenum&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;or-the-dose-makes-the-poison&quot;&gt;Or: the dose makes the poison&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, two quotes, one in English and one in German.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t worry, we’ll translate the German (this isn’t one of those 19th century novels that expects fluency in English, French, Latin, Italian, and German just to get through a page), and the same basic idea is found in the English quote. In German one of the words has a delightful history that is exposed when juxtaposed with an English translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Poisons in small doses are the best medicines; and the best medicines in too large doses are poisonous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theoncologist.alphamedpress.org/content/6/suppl_2/1.long&quot;&gt;William Withering, 18th century English physician, discoverer of digitalis (sort of), and proponent of arsenic therapy.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Alle Dinge sind Gift, und nichts ist ohne Gift; allein die dosis machts, daß ein Ding kein Gift sei.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zeno.org/Philosophie/M/Paracelsus/Septem+Defensiones/Die+dritte+Defension+wegen+des+Schreibens+der+neuen+Rezepte&quot;&gt; 1538, &lt;em&gt;Septem Defensiones&lt;/em&gt;, by Swiss physician Philippus Aureolus Theophrastus Bombastus von Hohenheim, also known as Paracelsus, “Father of Toxicology.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phrase “sola dosis facit venenum,” (usually rendered “the dose makes the poison” in English) is a Latinization of the German phrase above from Paracelsus. He wrote this in his “Seven Defenses” when he was fighting against accusations of poisoning his patients&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (malpractice court, it seems, is one of the oldest traditions in medicine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s my rough translation from Paracelsus’ German:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All things are poison, and nothing is not a poison. Only the dose makes the thing not a poison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throw in a couple of exclamation marks, italics, and fist pounds, and you have the makings of dialogue for the defendent in a 16th century &lt;em&gt;Law and Order&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;paracelsus&quot;&gt;Paracelsus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did this German guy have a Latin name?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one really knows. Von Hohenheim’s relationship with Latin and the humanistic antiquity it represented was complicated. Despite writing books with names such as &lt;em&gt;Septem Defensiones&lt;/em&gt;, he was known for refusing to lecture in Latin, preferring vernacular German instead, and the content of his books was invariably German.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; He publicly burned old Latin medical texts, along with their outdated ideas. My favorite version of the Paracelsus story is that the Latin name was first given to von Hohenheim by his friends, who were probably screwing with him, as they knew it would go against his iconoclastic bent. He used it (with a glint in his eye) as an occasional pen name, and it eventually stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this spirit I decided on the Latin slogan. It’s a bit of a post-post-modern jab at myself, medical tradition, and old bearded white men, who sometimes knew how to make fun of themselves and occasionally had good ideas despite their bearded whiteness.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Also, Latin is pretty. And regardless of language, the idea this phrase represents is possibly my favorite, in medicine and in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;poison-and-other-gifts&quot;&gt;Poison and other gifts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word for “poison” in German is &lt;em&gt;Gift&lt;/em&gt;. English “gift,” meaning “present,” comes from the same Proto-Indo-European root: &lt;em&gt;ghebh&lt;/em&gt;-, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/gift&quot;&gt;to give&lt;/a&gt;.” (Language is, after all, susceptible to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Divergent_evolution&quot;&gt;divergent evolution&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/languages/yoursay/false_friends/german/be_careful__its_a_gift_englishgerman.shtml&quot;&gt;amusingly&lt;/a&gt;). This dual meaning fits nicely with the general conceit — medicine and poison are two sides of the same coin, gifts in either case, to be used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lds.org/scriptures/dc-testament/dc/59.20&quot;&gt;with judgment, not to excess&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can keep going down the etymologic rabbit hole: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/poison&quot;&gt;poison&lt;/a&gt; comes from Proto-Indo-European &lt;em&gt;po(i)&lt;/em&gt;, “to drink,” the same root that gave us “potion” and “potable.” The Latin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/venom&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;venenum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from our quote, which eventually led to English “venom,” comes from Proto-Indo-European &lt;em&gt;wen&lt;/em&gt;, “to desire, strive for,” which made its way around to &lt;em&gt;wenes-no&lt;/em&gt;, “love potion,” and then to more general meaning as “drug, medical potion,” before finally assuming the modern meaning of a dangerous substance from an animal. I wonder if the evolution of these words from neutral or positive to negative reflects cycles of hope and disillusionment.  The history of medicine is filled with well-meaning, careful clinicians who were often simply wrong, as well as charlatans (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/medicaster&quot;&gt;medicasters&lt;/a&gt;, even).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, the word “medicine” has undergone remarkably little change in meaning. It comes from Proto-Indo-European &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/*med-&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;med&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “to take appropriate measures,” a root shared with “meditate,” “modest,” “accomodate,” and, of course, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etymonline.com/word/commode&quot;&gt;commode&lt;/a&gt;.” This is a complete way to think about how to practice and receive medicine: to take appropriate measures. The difficult part is deciding what “appropriate” means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what&quot;&gt;So what?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be a doctor shockingly soon (2020, two years after this writing). After residency I will most likely specialize in either hematology-oncology (blood cancer) or palliative care,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and in either case will help people decide which poison to take in an effort to feel better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crazily enough, some of the best treatments for some of the worst diseases are classical poisons, such as arsenic for some leukemias. Arsenic is what the lucky ones get to take — we have and regularly use other drugs that are much more dangerous. It’s not just drugs we poison people with, either. If you are fortunate enough to have the right kind of cancer, enough physical strength left in reserve, and a donor to make you eligible for a bone marrow transplant, get ready to become friends with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_particle_accelerator&quot;&gt;linear particle accelerator&lt;/a&gt;. We radiate the bone marrow until it gives up the ghost, then start over fresh, resurrection from the inside out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In palliative care it’s not so different, even though the goal is symptom management and not cure. An illustrative anecdote: during a palliative care rotation I was trying to help the physician do some calculations she had been doing by hand. I thought, “there has to be an online calculator for this…”, and pulled up several medical calculators from respected organizations. In every case, after I put in the drug and dose I wanted, the website would say something like,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hell no. We don’t touch that stuff. We’re not even going to do the calculation for you. If you need that medicine at that dose, call a palliative care doc. Consider our asses covered.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We dispense derivatives of poppy that make heroin look tame, administer amphetamines as antidepressants, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5867510/&quot;&gt;we’re starting to get good at using LSD&lt;/a&gt;. Poisons, all. Medicines, all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My smartass response when people ask me why I chose medicine is “power, drugs, money, and women.” It’s not entirely untrue: nobody else is allowed to use these tools on humans, whether fancy knives or fancy x-rays or fancy poisons; I will always have a job and a comfortable living no matter what happens to the economy (my wife and I have had kids since undergrad, which didn’t change my career goals but added an extra layer of responsibility); and chicks dig docs in uniform (the coat is white because it’s hot).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;to-sum-up&quot;&gt;To sum up:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the right hands, with respect and care, even the most dangerous substances can be tools for healing. I love that. So, for now at least, the pretentious phrase stays. Once more, with gusto: &lt;em&gt;Sola dosis facit venenum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Foxglove, the common name for &lt;em&gt;Digitalis purpura&lt;/em&gt;, has been used in medicine for centuries, most notably for “dropsy,” the edema (fluid accumulation) associated with heart failure and other conditions. &amp;lt;p&amp;gt; Withering was the one who figured out extraction methods, dosages, and side effects, and most thoroughly estabilshed it as a medicine rather than a folk remedy or poison, but it didn’t come out of nowhere. This is almost always the case: we stand on the shoulders of giants, aspirin comes from bark, etc.  &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;p&amp;gt; While I kind of wish the story that Withering stole it wholecloth from a local herbalist, Mother Hutton, was true, as it would fit my bias that most medicine is built on masculine appropriation of traditionally feminine arts without giving proper credit, this particular story &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0735-1097(85)80457-5&quot;&gt;does not appear to have any historical basis&lt;/a&gt;. (by the way: amniotomy hooks are sharpened crochet hooks, surgical technique is mostly translated sewing technique, pharmacy is fancy herbalism — and it’s not just in medicine: is a chef a man or a woman? What about a cook? Men make art, women make crafts. Etc., ad nauseum.) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The article from The Oncologist that gave us the Withering quote made the unfortunate mistake of saying he was a &lt;strong&gt;15th&lt;/strong&gt; century physician, which has, even more unfortunately, led to the persistence of the wrong century attached to his name in other publications. He was born in 1741, discovered digitalis in 1775, and died in 1799. &amp;lt;p&amp;gt; &amp;lt;/p&amp;gt; Because I’m completely insufferable: &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.findagrave.com/photos/2007/261/12542514_119024797099.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Withering Gravestone&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If we put on our 21st century lenses, we see that he was indeed poisoning his patients, but in good faith rather than out of quackery or malice. Paracelsus himself &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paracelsus.uzh.ch/general/paracelsus_life.html&quot;&gt;probably died from mercury intoxication&lt;/a&gt;, incurred from years of practicing alchemy, which was a perfectly respectable occupation for the learned of the time. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;One of the richest records of Paracelsus’ thought is &lt;em&gt;The Basle Lectures&lt;/em&gt;, which is written in Latin, but this is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paracelsus.uzh.ch/general/paracelsus_works.html&quot;&gt;collection of class notes&lt;/a&gt; taken by his students, who, like all good med students of the time, studied in Latin. The rest of the best work from and on Paracelsus &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paracelsus.uzh.ch/texts/paracelsus_reading.html&quot;&gt;is in German&lt;/a&gt;, as far as I can tell, with &lt;a href=&quot;https://yalebooks.yale.edu/book/9780300139112/paracelsus&quot;&gt;few exceptions&lt;/a&gt;. This is a source of irritation for this monolingual Anglophone. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ok, Paracelsus wasn’t bearded. But he should have been. I mean, look. &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/4/4a/Paracelsus.jpg/360px-Paracelsus.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paracelsus portrait&quot; /&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://getpalliativecare.org/whatis/&quot;&gt;Palliative care&lt;/a&gt; is all about helping people feel better when their disease or the treatment for it makes them feel crappy, physically and emotionally. Palliative care providers also know the legal system and end-of-life decision-making inside and out, and much of their work is counseling with worried and blindsided families who are trying to make decisions with and for their critically ill loved one. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;On the pronunciation: if you want to sound more Italian, then “soh-la dose-ees fa-cheet ven-ay-noom.” If you want to have fun in a different way, make the “c” in “facit” a hard “k” and throw in a comma and some emphasis: “soh-la dos-ees, &lt;strong&gt;fa-keet&lt;/strong&gt; ven-ay-noom.” Go ahead. Try it out loud. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="history" /><category term="balance" /><category term="humility" /><category term="medicine" /><summary>sola dosis facit venenum</summary></entry><entry><title>On the tools used to make this website</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/on-making-this-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the tools used to make this website" /><published>2018-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/on-making-this-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/on-making-this-website/">&lt;p&gt;I’m psyched about this little website. This post is about the tools and resources I used to make it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, this is a &lt;em&gt;static website&lt;/em&gt; made with &lt;em&gt;Jekyll software&lt;/em&gt; using the code editor called &lt;em&gt;Atom&lt;/em&gt; to write posts in &lt;em&gt;Markdown language&lt;/em&gt;. I also added a wishlist to the end, mostly to keep track of tools and tricks I may want to add.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;static-web&quot;&gt;Static Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.zipboard.co/how-to-start-with-static-sites-807b8ddfecc&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.digett.com/sites/default/files/images/static_site_0.png&quot; alt=&quot;The linked post has a nice overview of most of the static web services&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the internet we interact with on a day-to-day basis is “dynamic,” meaning we request something from a web server (e.g. click on a Facebook post or search for something on Amazon), which then talks to a database to pull all the relevant information and fill in a template (e.g. post content + comments, or product page with images, ratings, ads, etc.). The “static” web is much more old school: ask for something and the server gives you something, no database and comparatively little processing. Whatever is on the server has to be pretty much prebuilt and ready to go. This process is much simpler, faster, and more secure. The basic protocols are old and well established, unlikely to change or break.  For most online writing, such as a blog, static is the way to go, especially if it is likely to be consumed over a mobile internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/img/logo-2x.png&quot; alt=&quot;Jekyll&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is an open-source suite of open-source software for making static web pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is create a workflow that starts with just writing, followed by a predefined file structure and styling format to store all your stuff and make it pretty, and finally automatically translate it all into something a web browser can use. Jekyll also integrates nicely with GitHub, &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/about-github-pages-and-jekyll/&quot;&gt;which will host the site for free&lt;/a&gt;. GitHub also makes my favorite text editor, &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;. This leads to an integrated workflow: write in Atom → build in Jekyll+GitHub →  publish on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out about Jekyll from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ysbecca.github.io/programming/2018/05/22/py-wsi.html&quot;&gt;Rebecca Stone&lt;/a&gt;, who is writing the wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ysbecca/py-wsi&quot;&gt;py-wsi package&lt;/a&gt;. (This package makes massive digital pathology images tractable for deep learning.) As I read through her blog, I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://ysbecca.github.io/programming/2017/04/29/jekyll-migration.html&quot;&gt;this post on Jekyll and why she switched from WordPress&lt;/a&gt;. I read a few more posts like hers and was converted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some user-friendly Jekyll walkthroughs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://programminghistorian.org/en/lessons/building-static-sites-with-jekyll-github-pages&quot;&gt;Programming Historian: complete Jekyll and GitHub pages walkthrough for non-programmers&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Assumes you know absolutely nothing, explains terminology and has copy-paste code plus instructions for Windows &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Mac.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bwThn0rxv7M&quot;&gt;WebJeda: YouTube videos&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Modular and step-by-step. Sometimes it’s nice to watch someone go through the process in real time.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://evanwill.github.io/go-go-ghpages/0-prep.html&quot;&gt;University of Idaho Library: workshop, with blog posts and video&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Comparable to Programming Historian, with the benefit of dual coverage in the blog and video. The video is from a workshop where they walked through the process in real time, from nothing to something in around an hour, and the students asked a lot of the same questions I had.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;jekyll-themes&quot;&gt;Jekyll Themes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stole the layout of this site from &lt;a href=&quot;https://vangeltzo.com/index.html&quot;&gt;vangeltzo.com&lt;/a&gt;, whose beautiful design was Jekyll-ified (with permission!) by &lt;a href=&quot;https://taylantatli.github.io/Halve/&quot;&gt;TaylanTatli on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. I’m &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cbeauhilton/cbeauhilton.github.io/network/members&quot;&gt;not the only one&lt;/a&gt; using this theme, &lt;a href=&quot;https://drivenbyentropy.github.io/&quot;&gt;by&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ejieum.github.io/&quot;&gt;any&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://je553.github.io/&quot;&gt;means&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll themes are &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllthemes.org/&quot;&gt;abundant online&lt;/a&gt;, generally &lt;a href=&quot;https://taylantatli.github.io/Halve/halve-theme/&quot;&gt;easy to fork&lt;/a&gt; (“fork” means “copy for your own use without affecting the original”), and often &lt;a href=&quot;https://taylantatli.github.io/Halve/posts&quot;&gt;well commented&lt;/a&gt; so they are straightforward to customize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-this-theme&quot;&gt;Why this theme?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had two basic requirements for my theme. First, it had to be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leonardkoren.com/lkwh.html&quot;&gt;pretty&lt;/a&gt;. Second, I wanted a responsive split screen. “Responsive” means it can adapt itself to look nice on any device from a phone to a huge desktop monitor. The split screen confines the content to an easily readable width on the right and gives consistent navigation on the left. The 50/50 split screen is a little extreme, but I think I like it this way. If I ever want to change it to something like 66/33, it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TaylanTatli/Halve/issues/32&quot;&gt;quite  easy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll say more about specific choices, such as color, logo, and tagline in another post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;atom&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://avatars2.githubusercontent.com/u/1089146?s=200&amp;amp;v=4&quot; alt=&quot;Atom&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can write all of your code entirely within GitHub, which has its own text editor. The above tutorials use this approach to make it easy to start. There’s nothing wrong with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/JaretK&quot;&gt;fellow CCLCM student&lt;/a&gt; who is a much more legit programmer than me, recommended Atom, and I fell in love with only minimal doses of digital &lt;a href=&quot;http://harrypotter.wikia.com/wiki/Amortentia&quot;&gt;amortentia&lt;/a&gt;. It is ridiculously (almost dangerously) extensible, with community-supplied packages for an incredible breadth of programming languages and applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the nerds, for example, it has full support for LaTeX and all the typesetting, figure-making, citation-porn, and mathy goodness you can handle. One of my favorite workflows is to write something in Markdown to get the basics down with minimal fuss in an easier language, and then use Pandoc to convert it to LaTeX, followed by any futzing with the LaTeX (if you like) before outputting to PDF. You can also (!) combine the languages rather seamlessly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://u.arizona.edu/~selisker/post/workflow/&quot;&gt;post that details a full plain-text academic workflow with Atom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the poets, it can be a gorgeous and focused writing environment with infinitely more flexibility than Word. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://8bitbuddhism.com/2017/12/29/a-novel-approach-to-writing-with-atom-and-markdown/&quot;&gt;a post that describes how one creative writer uses Atom&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/packages/Zen&quot;&gt;Zen package&lt;/a&gt; alone should entice you Hemingway types, but also take a look at the writing assistance tools detailed in previous hyperlink or the hyperlink in the next paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the coolest thing is that I can have &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@sroberts/how-i-atom-12988bce8fce&quot;&gt;one central hub&lt;/a&gt; to do it all, with very little need for Word. If I use Atom to push things to GitHub, it also nearly replaces Google Docs for keeping everything safely in the cloud (caveat for the latter:as long as I don’t mind making my work public).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/dcurtis/markdown-mark/blob/master/png/208x128.png?raw=true&quot; alt=&quot;Markdown&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markdown is a “text-to-HTML conversion tool for web writers [that] allows you to write using an easy-to-read, easy-to-write plain text format, then convert it to structurally valid XHTML (or HTML).”  (click image or &lt;a href=&quot;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for source).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s inspired by the way people used to mark up their plain-text emails to make them more readable, with all the “#” and “-“ and “***” you can handle. Therefore, if you look at the source of something written in Markdown, it’s still pretty darn legible. Those of you who have read and written medical charts, many of these are still in common use (the “#” problem list, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are examples from a great &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adam-p/markdown-here/wiki/Markdown-Cheatsheet&quot;&gt;GitHub Markdown cheatsheet&lt;/a&gt;. First is the code and then the rendered text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Emphasis, aka italics, with *asterisks* or _underscores_.&lt;/code&gt;
Emphasis, aka italics, with &lt;em&gt;asterisks&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;underscores&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Strong emphasis, aka bold, with **asterisks** or __underscores__.&lt;/code&gt;
Strong emphasis, aka bold, with &lt;strong&gt;asterisks&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;underscores&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Combined emphasis with **asterisks and _underscores_**.&lt;/code&gt;
Combined emphasis with &lt;strong&gt;asterisks and &lt;em&gt;underscores&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Section with a hashtag:
# H1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section with a hashtag:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;h1&quot;&gt;H1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Section using underline style to accomplish the same thing:
Alt-H1
======
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Section using underline style to accomplish the same thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;alt-h1&quot;&gt;Alt-H1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty cool, eh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wishlistpossibilities&quot;&gt;Wishlist/possibilities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clickable Zen &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; mode (remove all hyperlinks - whether or not hyperlinks impair focus is &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=QJxeBAAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA79&amp;amp;lpg=PA79&amp;amp;dq=On+Measuring+the+Impact+of+Hyperlinks+on+Reading&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=Ih_zN17-Nh&amp;amp;sig=F47u2HB7nBavnD3amydmJo5wNB4&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjs0Pif1Z3dAhUKXa0KHcEeCucQ6AEwCXoECAEQAQ#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;hotly debated&lt;/a&gt;, he said with a meta-smirk).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clickable dark/light theme switch, a la &lt;a href=&quot;https://melangue.github.io/dactl//&quot;&gt;dactl&lt;/a&gt; (that black and white water drop button on the top right) or &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.webjeda.com/dark-theme-switch/&quot;&gt;Hagura&lt;/a&gt; (the text that reads “Dark/Light” at the bottom of the page is a button), for kinder day and night reading. The Hagura author wrote a tutorial &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.webjeda.com/dark-theme-switch/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Side notes, a la Tufte. &lt;a href=&quot;http://augmentingcognition.com/ltm.html&quot;&gt;Michael Nielsen’s blog&lt;/a&gt; has one implementation, and this &lt;a href=&quot;http://clayh53.github.io/tufte-jekyll/articles/15/tufte-style-jekyll-blog&quot;&gt;Tufte-ite Jekyll theme&lt;/a&gt; has another. I would probably have to reduce the page split from 50/50 to at least 66/33 for this to work properly.&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Or: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/philgruneich/barefoot&quot;&gt;Barefoot footnotes&lt;/a&gt; (click and they show up, like Wikipedia)&lt;/del&gt; Barefoot works very well, check out other posts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integrate fancy plugins&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drewsilcock.co.uk/custom-jekyll-plugins&quot;&gt;Overview of how to integrate non GitHub-approved plugins, with nice script that automates the integration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/del&gt; Went with Travis CI instead, using &lt;a href=&quot;http://joshfrankel.me/blog/deploying-a-jekyll-blog-to-github-pages-with-custom-plugins-and-travisci/&quot;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt;. I ended up breaking everything and fighting with it for a day, but it seems the whole issue was that the backend process of migrating from the github.io address to beauhilton.com was not instantaneous, and as soon as it was done I could change the internal reference to &lt;a href=&quot;https://beauhilton.com&quot;&gt;https://beauhilton.com&lt;/a&gt; and it came together. All that heroic hacking, for nothing…&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.janknappe.com/blog/Integrating-Academicons-with-Fontawesome-in-the-Millennial-Jekyll-template/&quot;&gt;Academicons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/roachhd/ed8da4786ba79dfc4d91&quot;&gt;Jekyll Scholar&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jgoodall/jekyll-scholar-extras&quot;&gt;Jekyll Scholar Extras&lt;/a&gt;, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://caesr.uwaterloo.ca//publications/index.html&quot;&gt;example with clickable BibTex and PDF downloads&lt;/a&gt; in publications page that makes me salivate.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bethallchurch.github.io/jupyter-notebooks-with-jekyll/&quot;&gt;Integrate Jupyter Notebooks seamlessly&lt;/a&gt; (the way people usually do it, which is probably fine and doesn’t require moar code, is to write up a plain-language explanation for the blog and link to the ipynb file on GitHub).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bdesham/reading_time&quot;&gt;Add estimated reading time to pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jekyll-plugins.com/plugins/simple-jekyll-search&quot;&gt;Add search bar&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robwierzbowski/jekyll-picture-tag&quot;&gt;Make the site pictures responsive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mademistakes.com/articles/jekyll-static-comments/#static-comments&quot;&gt;Add static comments to posts that would benefit from community&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;Get Table of Contents working for lengthy posts such as this one.&lt;/del&gt; Added this feature, though not in this particular post because the “# H1” Markdown examples screw it up.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="jekyll" /><category term="markdown" /><category term="atom" /><category term="hosting" /><category term="static web" /><category term="blog" /><category term="technical" /><summary>I’m psyched about this little website. This post is about the tools and resources I used to make it.</summary></entry></feed>
